Guide to the Norman Winestine Collection: Congregation Emanu-El and Fligelman's records 1883-1953
Montana Historical Society
Norman Winestine Collection: Congregation Emanu-El And Fligelman's
1883-1953
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 144
Winestine, Norman, 1895-1986
1.5 linear feet of shelf space
Norman Winestine (1895-1986) was a Helena, Montana, clothing store owner and member of the Jewish Congregation Emanu-El. Collection is divided into two main subgroups: records (1889-1947) of Congregation Emanu-El include correspondence, financial records, organizational materials, reports, Ladies Auxiliary records and cemetery association records; records (1883-1953) of Fligelman's Store include correspondence, financial records, and miscellany.
Norman Winestine was born February 15, 1895, in Wassaic, New York, and was raised in Waterbury, Connecticut. He received a bachelor's degree from Yale University and did post-graduate work in medieval history at Columbia University and at the newly established Dropsie College for Hebrew and Cognate Learning in Philadelphia. At Dropsie, Winestine studied Semitic language and Judaism. On April 18, 1918, Winestine married Belle Fligelman, daughter of Herman Fligelman, president and one of the founders of Helena, Montana's New York Dry Goods Company. In 1920, while living in Paris, France, Winestine accepted the offer of the position of general manager of the New York Dry Goods Company, popularly known as the New York Store. The store had been founded in 1882, under the name of H. Loble & Co., by Herman Fligelman and Henry Loble, both Romanian immigrants, and Robert Heller, an Austrian. The store was formally incorporated as the New York Dry Goods Company in 1890. When Winestine arrived in Helena in 1920, only Herman Fligelman of the original owners remained, Henry Loble having died in 1913 and Robert Heller having retired in 1920. The New York Store was destroyed by fire in 1928, but under Winestine's direction was rebuilt and renamed Fligelman's. Four years later, in 1932, founder Herman Fligelman died. Fligelman's was sold in 1958 to the J.M. McDonald Company. After moving to Helena, Winestine joined Congregation Emanu-El, a Jewish reform congregation. It had been reformed in August 1889 and a temple building completed in 1890. In April 1890 the congregation hired its first rabbi, Dr. Samuel Shulman of New York. Starting in 1925, Norman Winestine conducted the services on High Holy Days. Due to a decline in membership, the congregation was no longer able to support the maintenance of a temple, and decided to sell the building to the Montana Relief Commission in 1935. Winestine continued to conduct services for the few remaining members of the congregation, until after World War II.
This collection contains two subgroups. The Congregation Emanu-El Subgroup contains general correspondence (1917-1935); financial records (1902-1929); organizational materials and minutes (1889-1937), including those of the Ladies Auxiliary Society; and other items. The Fligelman's Subgroup includes general correspondence (1929-1935); financial records (1899-1942); and miscellany including a scrapbook (1886-1935) containing bills, letters, and clippings reflecting the history of Fligelman's and its predecessors, H. Loble and Company and the New York Dry Goods Company.
Arrangement by subgroup and series. Some material housed in Archives Map Case. See inventory below for more information.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
Photographs have been separated to the Photo Archives. See inventory below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Winestine, Norman, 1895-1986
Helena (Mont.)--Cemeteries; Helena (Mont.)--Church records; Helena (Mont.)--Commerce; Helena (Mont.)--Religious life and customs
Clothing trade--Montana--Helena; Jews--Montana--Helena; Dry-goods--Montana--Helena
Montana; Business, Industry, and Labor; Jewish Americans; Religion
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Congregation Emanu-El
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (includes Temple Imanu-El; L. Jacobs; H.S. Linfield; Montana Relief Commission; W.J. Butler; Moses Morris), 1917-1935 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Financial Records
    - Account book of Ladies Auxiliary Society, 1899-1947 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Financial reports, 1907-1925 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Journal, 1926, 1929 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Ledger of cemetery payments and dues, 1902-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Tax receipts; bank statements; checks; etc., 1925-1927 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Organizational Records
    - Certificates of incorporation for First Jewish Benevolent and Cemetery Association and Home of Peace Cemetery Association, 1903, 1931 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1910 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Minute books, 1889-1935 (Box-folder 1 / 9-10)
    - Minute book of Ladies Auxiliary Society, 1901-1937 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Rules of order, undated (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - Reports
    - Report of Rabbi Israel Klein to congregation, 1905 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - Miscellany
    - Blank stationery; Consolidated Collection Company form letter (incomplete), undated (Box-folder 2 / 4)
    - "Map of Hebrew Cemetery Helena" [Map Case See Folder MC 122-157], undated (Oversize-folder MC 122-157)
- Fligelman's
  - General Correspondence
    - "Copies of letters in answer to the many telegrams and letter received on opening of our new store" (removed from scrapbook), 1929 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
    - "Letters and telegrams regarding the fiftieth anniversary of Fligelman's" (removed from scrapbook), 1935 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
    - "Copies of letters in answer to the many letters and telegrams received on fiftieth anniversary of our store" (removed from scrapbook), 1935 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
    - "Some of the many letters received inquiring about the earthquakes" (removed from scrapbook), 1935 (Box-folder 2 / 8-9)
  - Financial Records
    - "Advertisements of the New York Store sales" (removed from scrapbook), 1899 (Box-folder 2 / 10)
    - Journal, 1918-1924 (Volume 1)
    - Ledger, 1911 (Volume 2)
    - Ledger (employee accounts), 1915-1918 (Volume 3)
    - Ledger (employee accounts), 1918-1920 (Volume 4)
    - Sales record, 1912-1923 (Volume 5)
    - Trial balance, 1911 (Box-folder 2 / 11)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs transferred to the Photo Archives (Box-folder 2 / 12)
  - Miscellany
    - Helena Independent "Special Fligelman's Edition;" Montana Record-Herald special Fligelman's insert, 1929 July (Volume 6)
    - Scrapbook (includes samples of early bills, letters, clippings, etc. about 1928 fire, 1929 reopening, 1935 earthquake, and 50th anniversary celebration), 1886-1935 (Box-folder 2 / 13)
    - Letterhead; invoice; lists of attendance at Fligelman's annual picnics; lists of guests at 1935 50th anniversary, 1940-1953 (Box-folder 2 / 14)
    - Stock certificates issued to New York Dry Goods Company, 1908-1929 (Box-folder 2 / 15)